Guide to the Stefan Zweig autographs collection, 1915-1942 AR 834
Center for Jewish History, Publisher.
Stefan Zweig autographs collection
1915-1942
Leo Baeck Institute
The collection consists mainly of correspondence from the famous Austrian writer Stefan Zweig with various friends and acquaintances, acquired by the Leo Back Institute in New York through donations and auctions. Also included are copies and a few printed materials.
4 folders
AR 834
Leo Baeck Institute Archives
Biographical Note
Stefan Zweig was born November 28, 1881, in Vienna, Austria into a family of wealthy industrialist. He studied in Austria, France, and Germany, earning his doctoral degree at the University of Vienna. After a short stop as literary editor of the Neue Freie Presse under Theaodor Herzl, Stefan Zweig became a most prolific and widely read critic and author of novels, biographies, plays, etc. In 1913 he settled in Salzburg, getting married to Friderike von Winternitz in 1914. During World War I he worked in the archives of the Austrian Armed Forces and became afterwards one of the great proponents of peaceful coexistence in Europe, living in Salzburg and travelling widely. After Austria’s Anschluss to Nazi Germany in 1938, Zweig became a British citizen, and in 1940, after a lecture tour in South America, he settled in Brazil. Disillusioned and isolated, Zweig committed suicide with his second wife, Charlotte E. Altmann, in Petrópolis, near Rio de Janeiro on February 23, 1942.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists mainly of correspondence from the famous Austrian writer Stefan Zweig with various friends and acquaintances, acquired by the Leo Back Institute in New York through donations and auctions. Also included are copies and a few printed materials.
The following individuals are mentioned in this collection:
Eisemann; Artur Fischer-Colbrie; Wolfgang Goetz; Dr. Guggenheim; Paul Hirsch; Henry Joske; Hellmut Meyer; Max Rieser; Ella Spiero; Oskar Schmitz; Frau Woltinski; and Paul Zesch.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in 2 series.
Series I: Originals, undated, 1915-1937, 1942
Series II: Copies and published materials, undated, 1916, 1937-1942
Separated Material
Photographs have been removed to the LBI Photograph Collection.
Obituaries and other clippings have been removed to the Stefan Zweig clipping collection, AR 1476.
Access Restrictions
Open to researchers.
Access Information
Readers may access the collection by visiting the Lillian Goldman Reading Room at the Center for Jewish History. We recommend reserving the collection in advance; please visit the LBI Online Catalog and click on the "Request" button.
Collection is digitized. Follow the links in the Container List to access the digitized materials.
Other Finding Aid
Copies of 9 catalog cards for the initial autographs collection in folder 1.
Zweig, Stefan, 1881-1942; Zweig, Friderike Maria Burger Winternitz, 1882-1971; Zweig, Charlotte Altmann; Jewish authors -- Austria; Brazil -- Emigration and immigration -- 1933-1945; Great Britain -- Emigration and immigration -- 1933-1945; Petrópolis (Brazil); Salzburg (Austria); Vienna (Austria); Archival materials; Correspondence; Photographs; Autographs; Manuscripts
Container List
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
Follow the links to access the digitized materials.
- Series I: Originals, undated, 1915-1937, 1942
  Included are 18 original autographs, mostly letters to friends and acquaintances, as well as a handwritten poem, "Vorgefühl", written on the eve of his suicide. Also included is an undated, unsigned typescript (2 p.), ‘Dank an die Bücher’.
  - 16 original autographs, mostly letters to friends and acquaintances, undated, 1915, 1926-1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Ein Dramatiker, undated
    - Dr. Guggenheim, 4/29/1930
    - Hellmut Meyer, 6/27/1931
    - Ella Spiero, ca. 1915
    - Oskar Schmitz, undated
    - Wolfgang Goetz, undated
    - Paul Hirsch, 5/31/1937
    - Redaktion, 7/8/1927
    - Artur Fischer-Colbrie, 12/21/1926, 1/15/1927, 4/25/1927, 5/7/1927, 9/26/1932, 6/9/1928
    - Frau Woltinski, 8/29/1923, 2/22/1933
  - Originals, undated, 1936-1942 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Max Rieser letter, undated
    - Paul Zesch letters, undated, 12/25/1941
    - Paul Zesch telegram, 9/8/1936
    - Paul Zesch transcript and English translations of two letters, undated
    - Poem, "Vorgefühl", written on the eve of his suicide, February 23, 1942
    - Typescript (carbon copy), unsigned: ‘Dank an die Bücher’, undated
- Series II: Copies and published materials, undated, 1916, 1937-1942
  This series contains copies of letters by Stefan Zweig to friends and acquaintances, as well as a facsimile copy of his suicide note. Also included are printed materials.
  - Copies of letters and other originals, 1916-1942 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Lieber guter Freund, 1/10/1916
    - Four letters to the book dealer Eisemann, undated, 1941
    - Draft for a speech, 1937
    - Copies of letters to Herr Marx and „Willi“, 1937-1941
    - Copy of Stefan Zweig’s suicide note, 2/22/1942
  - Others, undated, 1939-1940 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Two fliers, announcing public appearances by Stefan Zweig in New York, 1939
    - Photographs (copies), undated, 1940